So first, if you look at the level of wealth inequality, this is the share of total wealth going to the top 10 percent of wealth holders, so you can see the same kind of reversal between the U.S. and Europe that we had before for income inequality. So wealth concentration was higher in Europe than in the U.S. a century ago, and now it is the opposite. But you can also show two things: First, the general level of wealth inequality is always higher than income inequality. So remember, for income inequality, the share going to the top 10 percent was between 30 and 50 percent of total income, whereas for wealth, the share is always between 60 and 90 percent. Okay, so that's fact number one, and that's very important for what follows. Wealth concentration is always a lot higher than income concentration. Fact number two is that the rise in wealth inequality in recent decades is still not enough to get us back to 1910. So the big difference today, wealth inequality is still very large, with 60, 70 percent of total wealth for the top 10, but the good news is that it's actually better than one century ago, where you had 90 percent in Europe going to the top 10. So today what you have is what I call the middle 40 percent, the people who are not in the top 10 and who are not in the bottom 50, and what you can view as the wealth middle class that owns 20 to 30 percent of total wealth, national wealth, whereas they used to be poor, a century ago, when there was basically no wealth middle class. So this is an important change, and it's interesting to see that wealth inequality has not fully recovered to pre-World War I levels, although the total quantity of wealth has recovered. Okay? So this is the total value of wealth relative to income, and you can see that in particular in Europe, we are almost back to the pre-World War I level. So there are really two different parts of the story here. One has to do with the total quantity of wealth that we accumulate, and there is nothing bad per se, of course, in accumulating a lot of wealth, and in particular if it is more diffuse and less concentrated. So what we really want to focus on is the long-run evolution of wealth inequality, and what's going to happen in the future. How can we account for the fact that until World War I, wealth inequality was so high and, if anything, was rising to even higher levels, and how can we think about the future? So let me come to some of the explanations and speculations about the future. Let me first say that probably the best model to explain why wealth is so much more concentrated than income is a dynamic, dynastic model where individuals have a long horizon and accumulate wealth for all sorts of reasons. If people were accumulating wealth only for life cycle reasons, you know, to be able to consume when they are old, then the level of wealth inequality should be more or less in line with the level of income inequality. But it will be very difficult to explain why you have so much more wealth inequality than income inequality with a pure life cycle model, so you need a story where people also care about wealth accumulation for other reasons. So typically, they want to transmit wealth to the next generation, to their children, or sometimes they want to accumulate wealth because of the prestige, the power that goes with wealth. So there must be other reasons for accumulating wealth than just life cycle to explain what we see in the data. Now, in a large class of dynamic models of wealth accumulation with such dynastic motive for accumulating wealth, you will have all sorts of random, multiplicative shocks. So for instance, some families have a very large number of children, so the wealth will be divided. Some families have fewer children. You also have shocks to rates of return. Some families make huge capital gains. Some made bad investments. So you will always have some mobility in the wealth process. Some people will move up, some people will move down. The important point is that, in any such model, for a given variance of such shocks, the equilibrium level of wealth inequality will be a steeply rising function of r minus g. And intuitively, the reason why the difference between the rate of return to wealth and the growth rate is important is that initial wealth inequalities will be amplified at a faster pace with a bigger r minus g. So take a simple example, with r equals five percent and g equals one percent, wealth holders only need to reinvest one fifth of their capital income to ensure that their wealth rises as fast as the size of the economy. So this makes it easier to build and perpetuate large fortunes because you can consume four fifths, assuming zero tax, and you can just reinvest one fifth. So of course some families will consume more than that, some will consume less, so there will be some mobility in the distribution, but on average, they only need to reinvest one fifth, so this allows high wealth inequalities to be sustained. Now, you should not be surprised by the statement that r can be bigger than g forever, because, in fact, this is what happened during most of the history of mankind. And this was in a way very obvious to everybody for a simple reason, which is that growth was close to zero percent during most of the history of mankind. Growth was maybe 0.1, 0.2, 0.3 percent, but very slow growth of population and output per capita, whereas the rate of return on capital of course was not zero percent. It was, for land assets, which was the traditional form of assets in preindustrial societies, it was typically five percent. Any reader of Jane Austen would know that. If you want an annual income of 1,000 pounds, you should have a capital value of 20,000 pounds so that five percent of 20,000 is 1,000. And in a way, this was the very foundation of society, because r bigger than g was what allowed holders of wealth and assets to live off their capital income and to do something else in life than just to care about their own survival. Now, one important conclusion of my historical research is that modern industrial growth did not change this basic fact as much as one might have expected. Of course, the growth rate following the Industrial Revolution rose, typically from zero to one to two percent, but at the same time, the rate of return to capital also rose so that the gap between the two did not really change. So during the 20th century, you had a very unique combination of events. First, a very low rate of return due to the 1914 and 1945 war shocks, destruction of wealth, inflation, bankruptcy during the Great Depression, and all of this reduced the private rate of return to wealth to unusually low levels between 1914 and 1945. And then, in the postwar period, you had unusually high growth rate, partly due to the reconstruction. You know, in Germany, in France, in Japan, you had five percent growth rate between 1950 and 1980 largely due to reconstruction, and also due to very large demographic growth, the Baby Boom Cohort effect. Now, apparently that's not going to last for very long, or at least the population growth is supposed to decline in the future, and the best projections we have is that the long-run growth is going to be closer to one to two percent rather than four to five percent. So if you look at this, these are the best estimates we have of world GDP growth and rate of return on capital, average rates of return on capital, so you can see that during most of the history of mankind, the growth rate was very small, much lower than the rate of return, and then during the 20th century, it is really the population growth, very high in the postwar period, and the reconstruction process that brought growth to a smaller gap with the rate of return. Here I use the United Nations population projections, so of course they are uncertain. It could be that we all start having a lot of children in the future, and the growth rates are going to be higher, but from now on, these are the best projections we have, and this will make global growth decline and the gap between the rate of return go up. Now, the other unusual event during the 20th century was, as I said, destruction, taxation of capital, so this is the pre-tax rate of return. This is the after-tax rate of return, and after destruction, and this is what brought the average rate of return after tax, after destruction, below the growth rate during a long time period. But without the destruction, without the taxation, this would not have happened. So let me say that the balance between returns on capital and growth depends on many different factors that are very difficult to predict: technology and the development of capital-intensive techniques. So right now, the most capital-intensive sectors in the economy are the real estate sector, housing, the energy sector, but it could be in the future that we have a lot more robots in a number of sectors and that this would be a bigger share of the total capital stock that it is today. Well, we are very far from this, and from now, what's going on in the real estate sector, the energy sector, is much more important for the total capital stock and capital share. The other important issue is that there are scale effects in portfolio management, together with financial complexity, financial deregulation, that make it easier to get higher rates of return for a large portfolio, and this seems to be particularly strong for billionaires, large capital endowments. Just to give you one example, this comes from the Forbes billionaire rankings over the 1987-2013 period, and you can see the very top wealth holders have been going up at six, seven percent per year in real terms above inflation, whereas average income in the world, average wealth in the world, have increased at only two percent per year. And you find the same for large university endowments — the bigger the initial endowments, the bigger the rate of return. Now, what could be done? The first thing is that I think we need more financial transparency. We know too little about global wealth dynamics, so we need international transmission of bank information. We need a global registry of financial assets, more coordination on wealth taxation, and even wealth tax with a small tax rate will be a way to produce information so that then we can adapt our policies to whatever we observe. And to some extent, the fight against tax havens and automatic transmission of information is pushing us in this direction. Now, there are other ways to redistribute wealth, which it can be tempting to use. Inflation: it's much easier to print money than to write a tax code, so that's very tempting, but sometimes you don't know what you do with the money. This is a problem. Expropriation is very tempting. Just when you feel some people get too wealthy, you just expropriate them. But this is not a very efficient way to organize a regulation of wealth dynamics. So war is an even less efficient way, so I tend to prefer progressive taxation, but of course, history — (Laughter) — history will invent its own best ways, and it will probably involve a combination of all of these. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Thomas Piketty. Thank you. Thomas, I want to ask you two or three questions, because it's impressive how you're in command of your data, of course, but basically what you suggest is growing wealth concentration is kind of a natural tendency of capitalism, and if we leave it to its own devices, it may threaten the system itself, so you're suggesting that we need to act to implement policies that redistribute wealth, including the ones we just saw: progressive taxation, etc. In the current political context, how realistic are those? How likely do you think that it is that they will be implemented? Thomas Piketty: Well, you know, I think if you look back through time, the history of income, wealth and taxation is full of surprise. So I am not terribly impressed by those who know in advance what will or will not happen. I think one century ago, many people would have said that progressive income taxation would never happen and then it happened. And even five years ago, many people would have said that bank secrecy will be with us forever in Switzerland, that Switzerland was too powerful for the rest of the world, and then suddenly it took a few U.S. sanctions against Swiss banks for a big change to happen, and now we are moving toward more financial transparency. So I think it's not that difficult to better coordinate politically. We are going to have a treaty with half of the world GDP around the table with the U.S. and the European Union, so if half of the world GDP is not enough to make progress on financial transparency and minimal tax for multinational corporate profits, what does it take? So I think these are not technical difficulties. I think we can make progress if we have a more pragmatic approach to these questions and we have the proper sanctions on those who benefit from financial opacity. BG: One of the arguments against your point of view is that economic inequality is not only a feature of capitalism but is actually one of its engines. So we take measures to lower inequality, and at the same time we lower growth, potentially. What do you answer to that? TP: Yeah, I think inequality is not a problem per se. I think inequality up to a point can actually be useful for innovation and growth. The problem is, it's a question of degree. When inequality gets too extreme, then it becomes useless for growth and it can even become bad because it tends to lead to high perpetuation of inequality over time and low mobility. And for instance, the kind of wealth concentrations that we had in the 19th century and pretty much until World War I in every European country was, I think, not useful for growth. This was destroyed by a combination of tragic events and policy changes, and this did not prevent growth from happening. And also, extreme inequality can be bad for our democratic institutions if it creates very unequal access to political voice, and the influence of private money in U.S. politics, I think, is a matter of concern right now. So we don't want to return to that kind of extreme, pre-World War I inequality. Having a decent share of the national wealth for the middle class is not bad for growth. It is actually useful both for equity and efficiency reasons. BG: I said at the beginning that your book has been criticized. Some of your data has been criticized. Some of your choice of data sets has been criticized. You have been accused of cherry-picking data to make your case. What do you answer to that? TP: Well, I answer that I am very happy that this book is stimulating debate. This is part of what it is intended for. Look, the reason why I put all the data online with all of the detailed computation is so that we can have an open and transparent debate about this. So I have responded point by point to every concern. Let me say that if I was to rewrite the book today, I would actually conclude that the rise in wealth inequality, particularly in the United States, has been actually higher than what I report in my book. There is a recent study by Saez and Zucman showing, with new data which I didn't have at the time of the book, that wealth concentration in the U.S. has risen even more than what I report. And there will be other data in the future. Some of it will go in different directions. Look, we put online almost every week new, updated series on the World Top Income Database and we will keep doing so in the future, in particular in emerging countries, and I welcome all of those who want to contribute to this data collection process. In fact, I certainly agree that there is not enough transparency about wealth dynamics, and a good way to have better data would be to have a wealth tax with a small tax rate to begin with so that we can all agree about this important evolution and adapt our policies to whatever we observe. So taxation is a source of knowledge, and that's what we need the most right now. BG: Thomas Piketty, merci beaucoup. Thank you. TP: Thank you. (Applause)
Primero, si nos fijamos en el nivel de desigualdad de la riqueza, esta es la parte de la riqueza total que va al 10 % de los ricos, así que pueden ver el mismo tipo de reversión entre EE.UU. y Europa que teníamos antes de la desigualdad de ingresos. La concentración de la riqueza fue mayor en Europa que en EE.UU. hace un siglo, y ahora es lo contrario. Pero también pueden ver dos cosas: En primer lugar, el nivel general de desigualdad de la riqueza es siempre mayor que la desigualdad de ingresos. Recuerden, por la desigualdad de ingresos, la proporción que va al 10 % fue entre el 30 % y el 50 % de los ingresos totales, mientras que para la riqueza, la participación es siempre entre el 60 % y el 90 %. Bien, este es el primer hecho, y es muy importante para lo que sigue. La concentración de la riqueza es siempre mucho más alta que la del ingreso. El hecho número dos es que el aumento en desigualdad de la riqueza en las últimas décadas aún no es suficiente para igualar el de 1910. La gran diferencia en la actualidad, la desigualdad de la riqueza sigue siendo muy grande, con el 60 %, 70 % de la riqueza total para el 10 % superior, pero la buena noticia es que en realidad es mejor que hace un siglo, en el que en Europa fue de 90 % para el 10 % superior. Hoy lo que tenemos es lo que yo llamo el medio 40 %, los que no están en el 10 % superior y que no se encuentran en el 50 % inferior, y que pueden ver como la clase media rica que es propietaria del 20 % al 30 % de la riqueza total, riqueza nacional, y que eran pobres, hace un siglo, cuando no había básicamente, clase media rica. Este es un cambio importante, y es interesante ver que la desigualdad de la riqueza no se ha recuperado a niveles pre I Guerra Mundial, aunque la cantidad total de la riqueza sí se ha recuperado. ¿Bien? Este es el valor total de la riqueza en relación con los ingresos, y se puede ver que, en particular en Europa, estamos casi de vuelta a los niveles anteriores a la I Guerra Mundial. Así que en realidad hay dos diferentes partes de la historia aquí. Una tiene que ver con la cantidad total de la riqueza que acumulamos, y no hay nada malo per se, claro, en acumular una gran riqueza, y en particular si está más dispersa y menos concentrada. En lo que realmente queremos centrarnos es en la evolución de largo plazo de la desigualdad de la riqueza y lo que pasará en el futuro. ¿Cómo podemos explicar el hecho de que hasta la I Guerra Mundial, la desigualdad de la riqueza era tan alta y, en todo caso, se elevaba a niveles aún más altos, y qué podemos pensar hacia el futuro? Déjenme hacer algunas explicaciones y especulaciones sobre el futuro. Permítanme decir que quizá el mejor modelo para explicar por qué la riqueza está mucho más concentrada que el ingreso es un modelo dinámico, dinástico, en el que los individuos tienen un largo horizonte y acumulan riqueza por todo tipo de razones. Si la gente acumulara riqueza solo por razones de ciclo de vida, saben, para ser capaces de consumir cuando sean viejos, entonces el nivel de desigualdad de la riqueza debería estar más o menos en línea con el de desigualdad en los ingresos. Pero será muy difícil explicar por qué hay tanta mayor desigualdad de la riqueza que desigualdad de ingresos con un modelo de ciclo de vida, por lo que se necesita una historia en a las personas también les preocupe la acumulación de riqueza por otras razones. Por lo general, quieren transmitir su riqueza a la siguiente generación, a sus hijos, o, a veces quieren acumular riquezas por el prestigio, el poder que va con la riqueza. Debe haber otras razones para la acumulación de riqueza que el solo ciclo de vida para explicar lo que vemos en los datos. Ahora, en una gran clase de modelos dinámicos la acumulación de riqueza con tal motivo dinástico para la acumulación de riqueza, tendrá toda clase de azar, choques multiplicativos. Así, por ejemplo, algunas familias tienen un gran número de niños, por lo que la riqueza se dividirá. Algunas familias tienen menos hijos. También tienen choques a las tasas de interés. Algunas hacen enormes ganancias de capital. Algunas hicieron malas inversiones. Así que siempre tendrán cierta movilidad en el proceso de la riqueza. Algunas personas se moverán hacia arriba o hacia abajo. El punto importante es que, en cualquier modelo, para una variación dada de tales choques, el nivel de equilibrio de la desigualdad de la riqueza será una función rápidamente creciente de r menos g. Y de forma intuitiva, la razón por la que la diferencia entre la tasa de interés de la riqueza y la de crecimiento es importante, es que las desigualdades iniciales de riqueza se amplifican a un ritmo más rápido con una más grande r menos g. Tomen un ejemplo sencillo: con r igual a 5 % y g igual a 1 %, los ricos solo tienen que reinvertir 1/5 parte de sus ingresos de capital para asegurar que su riqueza aumenta tan rápido como el tamaño de la economía. Esto hace que sea más fácil construir y perpetuar grandes fortunas porque se pueden consumir 4/5 partes, asumiendo cero impuestos, y se puede reinvertir 1/5 parte. Por supuesto, algunas familias consumirán más que eso, algunas menos, por lo que habrá cierta movilidad en la distribución, pero, en promedio, solo tienen que reinvertir 1/5 lo que permite las altas desigualdades en riqueza se mantengan. Ahora, no se deben sorprender por la afirmación de que r puede ser más grande que g para siempre, porque, de hecho, es lo que pasó durante la mayor parte de la historia. Y es algo muy obvio para todos por una sencilla razón, que el crecimiento estuvo cerca del 0 % durante casi toda la historia. El crecimiento fue tal vez 0,1 %, 0,2 %, 0,3 %, con un muy lento crecimiento de la población y del producto per cápita, mientras que la tasa de interés del capital por supuesto no era 0 %. Era, para los activos de la tierra, que era la forma tradicional de activos en las sociedades preindustriales, era típicamente 5 %. Cualquier lector de Jane Austen sabría eso. Si quieres un ingreso anual de 1000 libras, debes tener un capital de 20 000 libras ya que el 5 % de 20 000 es 1000. Y en cierto modo, esta era la base misma de la sociedad, porque que r fuera más grande que g fue lo que permitió a los dueños de la riqueza y los activos vivir de sus ingresos de capital y hacer otra cosa en la vida no solo cuidar de su propia supervivencia. Ahora, una conclusión importante de mi investigación histórica es que el crecimiento industrial moderno no cambió este hecho básico tanto como se podría haber esperado. Claro, la tasa de crecimiento después de la Revolución Industrial rosa, típicamente, de 0 % a 1 % a 2 %, pero al mismo tiempo, la tasa de interés del capital también aumentó, por lo que la brecha entre las dos realmente no cambia. Así que durante el siglo XX, tenemos una combinación única de acontecimientos. Primero, una muy baja tasa de interés debido a los choques por las guerras de 1914 y 1945, la destrucción de la riqueza, la inflación, la quiebra durante la Gran Depresión, y todo esto redujo la tasa de rentabilidad privada de la riqueza a niveles inusualmente bajos entre 1914 y 1945. Y luego, en el período de posguerra, se tiene una inusualmente alta tasa de crecimiento, debido en parte a la reconstrucción. Ya saben, en Alemania, Francia, Japón, había crecimientos del 5 % entre 1950 y 1980 debido en gran parte a la reconstrucción, y también debido al gran crecimiento demográfico, el efecto de la generación 'baby boom'. Al parecer, eso no va a durar por mucho tiempo, o al menos el crecimiento de la población se supone que disminuirá en el futuro, y las mejores proyecciones que tenemos es que el crecimiento a largo plazo va a estar más cerca del 1 % al 2 % que del 4 % a 5 %. Así que si vemos esto, son las mejores estimaciones que tenemos de crecimiento del PBI mundial y la tasa de interés del capital, tasas promedio de interés sobre el capital, y pueden ver que durante la mayor parte de la historia de la humanidad, la tasa de crecimiento era muy pequeña, mucho más baja que la tasa de interés, y luego durante el siglo XX, es realmente el crecimiento de la población, muy alto en el período de posguerra, y el proceso de reconstrucción, los que trajeron crecimiento y una menor brecha con la tasa de interés. Aquí, he usado las proyecciones de población de Naciones Unidas, así que por supuesto no son seguras. Podría ser que empezáramos a tener un montón de niños en el futuro, y las tasas de crecimiento vayan a ser mayores, pero por ahora, estas son las mejores proyecciones que tenemos, y son que el crecimiento mundial declinará y la brecha entre la tasa de rentabilidad, subirá. Ahora, el otro hecho insólito durante el siglo XX fue, como he dicho, la destrucción, la tributación del capital, así que esta es la tasa antes de impuestos de utilidades. Esta es la tasa después de impuestos, y después de la destrucción, y esto es lo que trajo la tasa media de rentabilidad después de impuestos, y destrucción, bajo la tasa de crecimiento por un largo período. Pero sin la destrucción, sin impuestos, esto no habría sucedido. Así que permítanme decir que el equilibrio entre rendimientos del capital y crecimiento depende de muchos factores diferentes que son muy difíciles de predecir: la tecnología y el desarrollo de técnicas intensivas en capital. Ahora mismo, los sectores más intensivos en capital en la economía son el sector inmobiliario, la vivienda, el sector energético, pero podría ser que en el futuro tengamos muchos más robots en una serie de sectores y que esto sería una porción mayor del total de capital que el actual. Bueno, estamos muy lejos de esto, y por ahora, lo qué está pasando en los sectores inmobiliario y de energía, es mucho más importante para el capital total y la cuota de capital. La otra cuestión importante es que hay efectos de escala en la gestión de carteras, junto con la complejidad financiera, la desregulación financiera, que hacen que sea más fácil conseguir mayores tasas de interés para una cartera grande, y esto parece ser particularmente fuerte para multimillonarios, grandes fondos de capital. Solo para dar un ejemplo, esto viene de la clasificación de multimillonarios de Forbes durante el período 1987-2013, y pueden ver que los más ricos han estado creciendo al 6 % o 7 % al año en términos reales por encima de la inflación, mientras que el ingreso promedio en el mundo, el promedio de riqueza mundial, han aumentado en solo un 2 % por año. Y encuentran lo mismo para las grandes fundaciones universitarias, cuanto mayor el fondo inicial mayor la tasa de interés. Ahora, ¿qué se podría hacer? La primera cosa es que creo que necesitamos más transparencia financiera. Sabemos muy poco sobre la dinámica de la riqueza mundial, por lo que necesitamos la transmisión internacional de la información bancaria. Necesitamos un registro global de los activos financieros, una mayor coordinación en materia de impuestos a la riqueza, e incluso un impuesto sobre el patrimonio, con una pequeña tasa sería una manera de generar información para que entonces podamos adaptar nuestras políticas a lo que observemos. Y hasta cierto punto, la lucha contra los paraísos fiscales y la transmisión automática de la información nos está empujando en esta dirección. Hay otras formas de redistribución de la riqueza, que pueden ser tentadoras. Inflación: es mucho más fácil imprimir dinero que hacer una legislación impositiva, así que es muy tentador, pero a veces no se sabe lo que se hace con el dinero. Este es un problema. La expropiación es muy tentadora. Justo cuando sientes que algunas personas son demasiado ricas, simplemente las expropias. Pero no es muy eficiente organizar una regulación de la dinámica de la riqueza. La guerra es una manera aún mucho menos eficiente, así que prefiero los impuestos progresivos, pero, por supuesto, la historia (Risas) la historia inventará sus propias mejores maneras, y es probable que involucren una combinación de todo esto. Gracias. (Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Thomas Piketty. Gracias. Thomas, quiero hacerte 2 o 3 preguntas, porque es impresionante cómo dominas tus datos, por supuesto, pero básicamente sugieres que la creciente concentración de la riqueza es una especie de tendencia natural del capitalismo y que, si lo dejamos a su suerte, puede poner en peligro el propio sistema, por lo que estás sugiriendo que hay que actuar para implementar políticas que redistribuyen la riqueza, incluyendo las que acabamos de ver: impuestos progresivos, etc. En el contexto político actual, ¿qué tan realistas son? ¿Qué tan probable crees que es que se lleven a cabo? Thomas Piketty: Bueno, creo que si miramos atrás en el tiempo, la historia de la renta, el patrimonio y los impuestos está llena de sorpresas. No me impresionan mucho los que saben de antemano lo que va o no va a pasar. Creo que hace un siglo, mucha gente habría dicho que los impuestos progresivos a la renta nunca se darían y luego sucedió. Y hace cinco años, mucha gente habría dicho que el secreto bancario estaría con nosotros para siempre en Suiza, que Suiza era demasiado poderosa para el resto del mundo, y de repente se dieron unas sanciones de EE.UU. contra los bancos suizos para que se diera un gran cambio, y ahora nos estamos moviendo hacia mayor transparencia financiera. Así que creo que no es tan difícil coordinar mejor las políticas. Vamos a tener un tratado con la mitad del PBI mundial en la mesa, con EE.UU. y la Unión Europea, y si la mitad del PBI mundial no es suficiente para avanzar en la transparencia financiera y el impuesto mínimo para las ganancias corporativas multinacionales, ¿qué se necesita? Así que creo que no se trata de dificultades técnicas. Creo que podemos hacer progresos si tenemos un enfoque más pragmático a estas preguntas y tenemos las sanciones adecuadas para quienes se benefician de la opacidad financiera. BG: Uno de los argumentos en contra de tu punto de vista es que la desigualdad económica no es solo una característica del capitalismo, sino que es uno de sus motores. Así que si tomamos medidas para reducir la desigualdad, al mismo tiempo tendremos un menor crecimiento, potencialmente. ¿Qué respondes a eso? TP: Sí, creo que la desigualdad no es un problema per se. Creo que la desigualdad hasta un punto en realidad puede ser útil para la innovación y el crecimiento. El problema es que es una cuestión de grado. Cuando la desigualdad se hace demasiado extrema, a continuación, se vuelve inútil para el crecimiento e incluso puede llegar a ser mala porque tiende a conducir a alta perpetuación de desigualdad en el tiempo y baja movilidad. Y por ejemplo, el tipo de concentraciones de riqueza que teníamos en el siglo XIX y más o menos hasta la I Guerra Mundial en todos los países europeos no era, creo, nada útil para el crecimiento. Fue destruida por una combinación de eventos trágicos y cambios de política, y esto no impidió que el crecimiento se diera. Y también, la desigualdad extrema puede ser mala para nuestras instituciones democráticas si crea un acceso muy desigual a la voz política, y la influencia del dinero privado en la política estadounidense, creo, es un motivo de preocupación en este momento. Así que no queremos volver a esta clase de extremo, de desigualdad pre I Guerra Mundial. Tener una cuota decente de la riqueza nacional para la clase media no es mala para el crecimiento. En realidad, es útil tanto por razones de equidad como de eficiencia. BG: Dije al principio que tu libro ha sido criticado. Algunos de datos han sido criticados. Parte de tu elección de conjuntos de datos ha sido criticada. Se te ha acusado elegir datos intencionadamente para soportar tu caso. ¿Qué respondes a eso? TP: Bueno, respondo que estoy muy feliz de que este libro haya estimulado el debate. Es parte de su propósito. Mira, la razón por la que pongo todos los datos en línea con todo el cálculo detallado es para que podamos tener un diálogo abierto y transparente, debatir sobre esto. He respondido punto por punto a cada preocupación. Permítanme decir que si fuera a reescribir el libro hoy, hubiera realmente concluido que el aumento de la desigualdad de la riqueza, particularmente en EE.UU., en realidad ha sido más alta que lo que reporto en mi libro. Hay un estudio reciente realizado por Saez y Zucman que muestra, con nuevos datos que no tenía en el momento del libro, que la concentración de la riqueza en EE.UU. ha aumentado incluso más de lo que reporto. Y habrá otros datos en el futuro. Algunos irán en diferentes direcciones. Mira, nosotros ponemos en línea casi todas las semanas un nueva serie actualizada en la base de World Top Income y seguiremos haciéndolo en el futuro, en particular de los países emergentes, y doy la bienvenida a todos aquellos que quieran contribuir a este proceso de recolección de datos. De hecho, claramente estoy de acuerdo que no hay suficiente transparencia sobre la dinámica de la riqueza, y una buena manera de tener mejores datos sería contar con un impuesto sobre el patrimonio con una pequeña tasa, para empezar por lo que todos podamos estar de acuerdo sobre esta importante evolución y adaptar nuestras políticas a lo que observemos. Los impuestos son fuente de conocimiento, y eso es lo que más necesitamos en estos momentos. BG: Thomas Piketty, merci beaucoup. Gracias. TP: Gracias. (Aplausos)